#現在豬肉太貴啦 我去搞一隻雞來吃 雞比較便宜一點
Pork is too expensive these days. Let me get a chicken. Chicken is cheaper.
#去買一隻來
I'll buy one.
#跟那個大嬸說了一下 她說雞就在這裡
I've talked to the Auntie. She said that the chickens are right here.
#她叫我們隨便抓 抓到哪隻秤一下就好啦
She asks us to catch whichever we like. We just weigh it then.
#誒呀
Eya?
#有一個小一點的那個 不是母雞
There's a smaller one. It's not a hen.
#那個肉肯定很好吃
It must be very tasty.
#不費吹灰之力 就把你抓起來啦
Catching you, is a piece of cake.
#去燒點開水來
Let me boil some water.
#你看 這個雞
Look! The chicken,
#很漂亮哦
is very pretty.
#不大又不小 剛剛好
The size is just right, not too big, not too small.
#應該差不多兩斤多到三斤
It should weigh at least a kilogram, perhaps one and a half.
#這頭不要
I don't want its head.
#給 賞給你們吃 (註︰這個「賞」字....)
I give, bestow it upon you.
#我先割幾刀給它 割一下它的那個 就比較入味
Let me cut it a few times. Then, you know, the flavour can be better absorbed.
#全身都要割
Cut everywhere.
#先腌一下 再來
Marinate it first, and then...
#再來 燒
and then, grill it.
#先切點這個薑絲
Shred some, you know, ginger.
#薑絲
Shredded ginger.
#加點料酒
Some cooking wine.
#加點鹽
Some salt.
#夠了夠了夠了 不要那麼多鹽
Enough, enough, enough! Not too much salt.
#加點這個 生抽
Add some, light soy sauce,
#搞多點生抽
more soy sauce.
#好像還差甚麼
Do I miss something?
#大蒜 對
Oh yea! Garlic!
#搞幾個大蒜進去
Put some garlic.
#把這個大蒜
So I put some garlic,
#放點上去
onto the chicken
#給它按按摩
Give it a massage.
#這個腌的話差不多要腌一個小時哦
To marinate it, it takes almost an hour to marinate it.
#一個小時才可以入味
The flavour needs an hour to be fully absorbed.
#現在都聞得到很香啦
It already smells very good now.
#好啦 我去準備點黃泥
Alright! I'll fetch some mud.
#去放在桌子上 等下不要被狗吃掉了
I'll put it on the table. Otherwise, it will be eaten up by the dogs.
#那個鋤頭都不佑道被老弟搞到哪裡去了
My younger brother has placed the hoe to somewhere only God knows.
#我隨便 我去搞點那黃泥回來
I just, I'm going to get some mud.
#現在夠啦
Now that's enough.
#這個泥好重
It's so heavy.
#先把這個黃泥 加點水先
The mud, mix it with water first.
#給它們攪拌均勻
Mix them well.
#哎呀
Aya!
#弄得一褲子都是
It spills onto my trousers.
#好啦 這個黃泥可以啦
Alright! The mud is okay now.
#等下我們把那雞裹起來
Then you can wrap the chicken.
#手上好多泥 我洗一下手
My hands are covered with mud. Let me wash my hands.
#嗯 搞到我一臉都是
Um! My face too!
#你看 現在 現在過了一個小時了 已經腌好了
Look! Now, now an hour is passed. It should be well marinated.
#把這個生薑 放到它肚子裡面去
Let me put the ginger, into its stomach,
#然後再把這個鍚紙把它裹起來
and then wrap it with the aluminium foil.
#嘿 把你裹起來
Huh! Wrap you!
#還有一點醬汁 別浪費了
Here's some more sauce, don't waste it.
#把這腳
The feet...
#拐一下
Twist it.
#嗯
Um!
#就這一坨
So it's a bulk.
#我們把它裹上黃泥
Let's wrap it with the mud.
#裹上黃泥它就
With the mud,
#動不了了 (註︰這個不明白，沒有黃泥雞就會跑掉嗎？)
it can't move.
#把它一層一層的把它疊好
Cover it, with layers of mud.
#小狗 你想吃嗎
Puppy, do you want it?
#香不香這個黃泥
Does the mud smell good?
#不夠水
Not enough water.
#夠了
It's enough.
#摸不到
You can't.
I can.
#摸一下來哇
Come on you try!
#全部黏在手上
It sticks onto your hands.
#你不會摸 我來摸
You just can't. Let me do it.
#搞點水
Some more water.
#水不夠
I need more water.
#放放 放點水
Some, some, some more water.
#就一點
Not too much!
#摸一摸
Make it even.
#你看 現在摸的[SIC]像個球一樣子
Look! It looks like a ball now.
#嗯 這樣就可以啦
Um! It's alright now.
#上烤架
Onto the grill!
#現在野外禁止用火
It's forbidden to set a fire outside these days.
#所以我們只能在家裡烤
So we can only grill at home.
#好 這個做好啦
Alright! It's ready now.
#先把那個
I'll fetch the,
#那個球那個[SIC]來
fetch the ball.
#嗯
Um...
#我們直接燒就可以啦
We can just grill it here.
#先加點稻草
Put some straw here,
#燒一下
and burn it.
#打火機都不見啦
The lighter has gone missing.
#我用那個煤氣火點著
So I burn it with the stove.
#先燒一下
Burn it,
#讓它定型
to fix its shape.
#你看這個豬天天吃那個狗吃的飯哦 才那麼胖
Look at the pig. It eats the, the meal of the dogs. That's why it's so fat.
#其他都瘦了 就它胖
The other pigs are getting skinny, but it is not.
#小豬
Piggy!
#好不好吃
Does it taste good?
#摸一下耳朵
Let me touch your ear.
#那麼壞
Naughty!
#上次我們堆的這個水池
That's the pond we made last time.
#被這個豬當成了游泳池
It's the pig's swimming pool now.
#天天在這裡洗澡
It's taking a bath here everyday.
#現在把玉米放下去
Put the corns in.
#烤一下
Grill them.
#這很香哦 這個
It smells really good, you know.
#這樣就香味十足
Then it smells super good.
#你看 這是攝影小哥家的番薯
Look! These are the sweet potatoes from Mr. Cameraman's place.
#搞幾個去烤一下
Let's grill some of them.
#把這個撈起來 這個雞撈起來
Take it out. Take out the chicken.
#應該熟啦
It should be done now.
#這筲箕都快燒掉啦
The dustpan is almost burnt.
#先看一下這個雞怎麼樣
Let's have a look at the chicken first.
#這個雞
The chicken,
#有點燒焦啦 哦
is a bit burnt.
#那麼燒
Too bad.
#肯定烤了太久啦
It's grilled too long.
#哇 這個好香啊 這個
Wa! It smells so good!
#哇 真的好香啊
Wa! It smells really good!
#這個玉米要等一下
I'll leave the corns here for a while.
#把它
Let me,
#拿回去
take it back.
#啊 喝點這個
Ah! Let's drink some,
#肥仔快樂水
chubby happy drink.
#杯子太小啦
The cups are too tiny,
#沒辦法
well.
#那個雞腿
The chicken leg,
#吃那個雞腿呀
take the chicken leg!
#你吃
No, you take it.
#好 我吃
Okay, I'll take it.
#嗯 好香啊 沒燒焦的地方
Oh it's so nice, I mean the parts which are not burnt.
#燒焦了就不好吃啦
Otherwise it's another story.
#這肉是很好吃啊
In fact the meat tastes really good.
#但是這裡燒焦啦
But it's a bit burnt here.
#吃沒燒焦的地方
I'll eat the good parts.
#這外面的燒焦了就不能吃
The burnt skin is not edible.
#太久沒烤東西啦
It's too long since our last grilling.
#都掌握 掌握不了火候啦
My skills, my skills are getting rusty.
#好啦
Alright!
#今天的視頻就到這裡啦
The video ends here.